Inventory of the Ethyl Corporation records, 1823-1983
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Ethyl Corporation records
1823-1983
Ethyl Corporation
00548
11.10 cubic feet (25 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
System Requirements
Training films -- film -- 16mm and 8mm.
20th Anniversary observation -- phonodisc -- 33 1/3 rpm.
Kettering speech -- phonodisc -- 33 1/3 rpm.
History of the Ethyl Corporation
The Ethyl Corporation, chartered in Delaware in 1924, originated from the research efforts of scientists and chemical engineers Charles F. Kettering and Thomas Midgeley, Jr. In 1921, Midgley and Kettering discovered tetraethyl lead as an anti-knock agent in automobile engines. Kettering named this tetraethyl lead "Ethyl" gasoline and made it available to the public in 1923. Midgley and Kettering founded the General Motors Chemical Company to provide distribution of the gasoline. Standard Oil Company of New Jersey joined General Motors Chemical in its manufacturing to create Ethyl Corporation in 1924.
Kettering served as president of the corporation, serving until 1925. Midgley served as vice-president and general manager until his death in 1944. James Boudreau served as vice-president and director of public relations until 1966. Earl Botholomew, an engineer, developed several important patents, including a special mixture of bromine and chlorine and an engine that could use tetraethyl lead and meet clear air regulations. In 1962, Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Company bought out Ethyl Corporation.
Scope and Content
Collection contains mainly historical materials gathered by Boudreau for the history of the petroleum industry and corporation exhibits. Collection includes account books, stock certificates, newspapers and maps, advertisements, and other materials gathered by Boudreau and deal mostly with the petroleum industry in Pennsylvania (1823-1960). Also included is Thomas Midgley's correspondence (1919-1952) regarding scientific research and business matters; photographs and glass slides of research and equipment (1923-1943); publications and speeches (1923-1983); 10 8mm and 26 16mm service and training films; and 5 33 1/3 rpm phonograph records of a 1940 Charles Kettering speech and a 20th anniversary observation.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by the Ethyl Corporation at the date of processing.
Additional Information
Finding aid available in repository.
Acquisition Information
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of select material from this collection are available at http://digitalcollections.uwyo.edu/luna/servlet/uwydbuwy~14~14.
Access Terms
Boudreau, James.;; Gasoline -- Research -- United States.; Gasoline -- United States -- Anti-knock and anti-knock mixtures.; Petroleum industry and trade -- United States.; Petroleum industry and trade -- Pennsylvania.;; Buiness records.; Motion pictures.; Negatives.; Phonograph records.; Photographs.;;; Midgley, Thomas, 1889-1944.
Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Businesses and Corporations; Science, Technology and Health; Energy Production
Container List
- Container List PDF
  The American Heritage Center is in the process of converting its older container lists to a more accessible format. This link is to an older version of a container list.
  - Link to Container List (PDF)
- Series VI. Audi-Visual Material
  Contains 16mm motion picture service and training films and audio recordings.
  - To Set the Record Straight: A Medical and Technical Documentary on Lead in the Environment, 1971 (Box 26)
  - Leaded vs. Unleaded Gasoline? The Facts and the Myths, undated (Box 26)
  - Training Film Series:
    - "Carburetor" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 27)
    - "Cooling System" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 27)
    - "Distributor" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 27)
    - "Electrical System" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 27)
    - "Fuel Injection" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1957 (Box 27)
    - "Preventing Carburetor Deposits" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1959 (Box 27)
    - "Preventing Carburetor Icing" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1959 (Box 27)
    - "Valves" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 27)
  - Gasoline for Everybody, 1947 (Box 27)
  - Handling Ethyl Drums, 1958 (Box 27)
  - One Good Turn Deserves Another, 1953 (Box 27)
  - At Your Command! A Report to American Farmers, undated (Box 28 and 31)
  - Looking Forward: A Film Story of a New Magic in Agriculture, 1946 (Box 28)
  - Masters of the Soil, undated (Box 28)
  - Unloading Ethyl Tank Cars, 1957 (Box 28)
  - Fundamentals of Fuel Knock, 1951 (Box 29)
  - Looking Ahead, 1946 (Box 29)
  - Old MacDonald Had a Farm, 1944 (Box 29)
  - Magic in Agriculture: A Film Story about Farm Chemurgy, 1946 (Box 29)
  - This is Our Land: A Story about Soil Conservation, 1946 (Box 29)
  - Automotive Series:
    - "Spark Plugs" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 30)
    - "Gasoline Part 1, Volatility" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 30)
    - "Gasoline Part 2, Knocking and Preignition" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1956 (Box 30)
    - "Cooling System" Training Film Series Engine Components Gasoline Characteristics, 1957 (Box 30)
  - Ethyl Products Sales Clinic, undated (Box 31)
  - Mixing Plants Operations, 1952 (Box 31)
  - You're the Doctor, 1951 (Box 31)
  - Ethyl Mixing Plant Maintenance, 1958 (Box 32)
  - Getting Ahead of Tomorrow, undated (Box 32)
  - Pattern for Progress: The Story of a Farm and a Family, 1941 (Box 32)
  - Pick Your Tomorrow, 1954 (Box 32)
  - Twin Power, undated (Box 32)
  - All the Answers, 1937 (Box 33)
  - For Better Performance, 1954 (Box 33)
  - The Long Road A Film Story about High Compression Power, 1946 (Box 33)
  - Safe Handling of Ethyl Fluid, 1954 (Box 33)
  - There is a Difference, undated (Box 33)
  - 2=3, 1952 (Box 33)
  - Audio:
    - "Looking Forward" speech by Charles F. Kettering (phonograph record), April 10, 1940 (Box 34)
    - Transcription of tape recording of 20th Anniversary Observance, parts 1-7 (33 speed photograph records), undated (Box 34)
    - Unidentified (magnetic tape), undated (Box 34)